Hello and welcome back to another
video with  itsDrdan and what we're
going to be looking at is observation.
Now, when it comes to what we were
talking about before, in the previous
video, was that we have the world
around us, it's constantly changing.
Now, when we are taking observations,
what exactly are we doing with it?
Well, we're recording it.
When you go into the lab for the
first time, or the tenth time, or the
millionth time, or into a hospital
room, or into a clinic, You're
constantly observing around you.
You need to be able to see what
do you need to address now?
What is the important thing that's
happening around you, right?
So one of the things I always ask my
students in person is that if you have a
patient that comes up to you, let's say
you want to be a healthcare friar, let's
say you want to be a nurse, which a lot
of students generally do in this course.
And you have, what is your
patient going to do the second
they see you for the first time?
Especially if they need help, they
are going to list off every single
thing that is wrong with them.
They could be like, Oh,
I'm not feeling too good.
I have a bruise on my arm.
Oh, I got this cut on my finger.
Oh, I got this.
And then one of the things is going
to be the most important, right?
You need to be able to address
what's the most important thing.
You need to be able to
decipher information.
break it down, right?
This is why you go through college.
This is one of the reasons why you're
trying to critically evaluate things
because it's not always this natural skill
that we're all just born with, right?
We have to learn it.
We have to do it through experience.
So we have to be able to take
observations and then how do we do that?
Well, you can do it in all kinds of ways.
You do it on a regular basis.
You might be doing it even right
now, whether you realize it or not.
One of those things are
as qualitative, right?
So what is the quality of something?
So like I said, you might
be doing it right now.
What is the quality of me
speaking to you right now?
You're like, oh, this guy is
like, maybe he's doing a good job.
Oh, he's really bad.
Like, that's a quality.
Right?
Uh, if you buy something off,
let's say Amazon or eBay, they
list the quality of the item.
It could be brand new.
It could be very good.
It could be okay.
It's used.
Those are qualities, right?
And those affect how you react
to buying that item, the quantity
qualitative or quantitative, right?
So how many of these things are,
how are you measuring it directly?
Right?
How, what's the number value behind that?
So when you might.
The, let's say you, let's go
back to the patient example
that you're taking care of.
You might see like, Oh, they
seem to be a little sluggish.
So what do you do to try
to back up the numbers that
they're not feeling quite right?
You take their blood pressure,
you look at their heart rate.
So those are the
quantitative measurements.
You try to take their temperature.
You're looking exactly what, how can
you do to back up your observation
as someone taking care of somebody
and you can do this all around us.
Now, what do you do with that?
Well, you're going to be making
a hypothesis behind that data
that you're collecting, right?
Something that you can present to, let's
say the doctor or your supervisor or
whoever it is that's working above you.
You have to be able to take data with you.
And to back up what you're saying, you
have to be able to explain that data.
Now, a really good hypothesis is
something that can be proven wrong.
And that's really, really hard
for a lot of people who in here
really likes to be proven wrong.
Almost nobody, look on the news
anytime you see a political anything.
No one likes to admit that they're wrong.
Hypotheses are all about
something that's falsifiable.
As a scientist or someone in a
science profession, even as a
healthcare giver, you are a scientist.
is that you need to be okay
with being proven wrong.
That's the point of science, right?
You want to be proven wrong, right?
If you have this thing that's
concrete and it's right, amazing.
But people, other people should be
doing the due diligence to check
your numbers, to double check
that what you found is correct.
And if it is amazing, right?
Then it can move forward.
Now, how do we determine the hypothesis?
Well, You might take all
these initial results.
You kind of see these things and you
might think like, Oh, maybe this person,
like the other kind of sluggish, they're
not quite in the right head space.
Maybe it's, maybe you think like they have
a concussion or, or something like that.
So what do you do?
You might send them to maybe get an MRI
or get different, maybe get blood work
done or all kinds of different tests.
These are your experiments.
Right?
And that's what they do
every day in the hospital.
They're taking blood tests,
doing all these different things.
Those are experiments are being
done on the date on the daily.
Now, once those experiments are
done, you got new knowledge.
You're like, Oh, well,
everything looks normal or,
Hey, this is really, really bad.
We need to go into surgery right
now based on that new knowledge.
Right?
It's all about timing.
So experiments and new
knowledge is used all the time.
So we like to be able to
test things we observe.
It's important to be able to get those
others of the observation skills down
because they're going to be used.
What exactly do we need for an
experiment or for a medical test?
How do, what do we do?
Right?
So you need to be able to have
a hypothesis and this needs to
be done on a measurable quality.
So if you're like in, let's say
the laboratory setting, right?
You need to be able to, Have something
that you can actually look at and
measure with what you have on hand.
Whether it's the volume of something,
maybe the concentration of something,
uh, maybe the mass of another thing.
You have to be able to measure a property.
Whatever that might be, something
that's observable, something you
can see, something you understand,
something you can actually talk about.
Now, whenever you do have this, you got
to have some kind of control, right?
Or a standard to refer against,
against to do something, right?
If you were to take, let's say,
blood work of a person, Right.
You have a standard or a control area
that this person should be in, right?
This is the normal area that a human
being should be in now, if they're higher
or lower than that, that gives you a lot
of information that's either good, bad.
Maybe it's like, it's okay.
It's sometimes out of the normal
range, but the doctors and
nurses are supposed to know that.
Now, there's also different variables,
how we can talk about that, we have
independent and dependent, right,
independence like living on your
own, doing your own thing, that's
something that's controlled by the
experimenter or you, right, so you
have complete control over that.
So, maybe one thing, for example,
is let's say if you wanted to,
uh, Say test blood samples, right?
You could take different volumes
of blood and that could be an
independent variable because you're
controlling the volumes, right?
So that's one option.
Dependent would be something
that's directly reflecting
on that independent variable.
So it's, it's based on that.
One example or analogy I like to
use is if you are a parent, You are
the independent individual, but your
child, or maybe your sibling, maybe
you have a little brother or sister,
they're dependent on you, right?
You gotta feed them, you gotta
take care of them, you gotta
pick them up from school, right?
Anything that you do affects them.
So, a dependent variable is
affected by the independent.
So going back to the health example,
if you're taking volumes, well,
what's going to get affected?
Well, the mass would get affected
by the volume, maybe potentially
concentrations could change.
There's all kinds of little
things that you might see.
So that's kind of the idea now
going beyond just hypothesis
and doing simple experiments.
Science is something that has
evolved over hundreds of years, and
it's always been something that's
all about trying to make sure it's
reproducible and that it's something
that either is proven or it's not.
You know, we're not trying to convince
people that everything is right.
That's not always true.
So, let's say you have a bunch
of observations and many people
are taking the same observations.
Eventually, if it's something that is
constant and it's something that never is
disproven, this is referred to as a law.
So these are something that can be
used to predict new observations,
like no matter what, you know, we
do this one thing, it's always going
to be doing the exact same result.
And we have that observation and we
can use it to define other findings.
So what could be an example of that?
Well, if you kind of think of, let's
say if I have a pencil and I drop it.
It's always doing the exact same thing.
What's describing that well known
as the law of gravity, right?
When Isaac Newton first put that
into words, not that gravity didn't
exist until the 1600s, it's always
been there, but it's something
that's always been observed, but it
wasn't put into actual scientific
explanation, but it's always here on
any planet or any large body of mass.
Is has a force of attraction, right?
So that could be defined as gravity.
So if an apple falls from a tree or
raindrops fall from the sky, they're
always going to come downwards.
So when it comes to the
law of gravity, right?
All matter is somewhat attracted
to each other and it's done
by the gravitational force.
So it's our gravitational force.
So if I drop my pencil or
drop a pen or anything.
Right?
You will see it come back down.
Now, if you have taken a physics class
or if you one day have to take classical
physics, you will constantly use the
gravity constant to be able to describe
how matter, let's say like rockets or
planes or anything that's flying is
going to behave because you have to
take into account how gravity works.
Now, when it comes to that as well, right?
We don't always have laws.
Sometimes we also have
scientific theories.
Right now, when it comes to a
theory, this is something that,
oh, I've seen this happen many,
many times over and over, right?
My hypothesis that I've had is consistent.
I've been proving this
the same way for 10 years.
But, maybe it's not quite a law,
but, because there's always a
chance it could be disproven.
But it's consistent, right?
So when it comes to a theory, this
is something that we constantly
use to explain something, right?
Those observations can be explained.
Um, it answers the what
and the why, right?
Which is the fantastic part about it.
Now, like I said, all
these can be disproven.
Theories change.
If you ever go back, let's say, whenever
you take your biology course, if you
have taken or not or yet, one really cool
thing is the theory of evolution, right?
Notice how that says theory.
Evolution is not a law.
Evolution, when it first was proposed by
Darwin, he wasn't the first to propose it.
There was many other, there was
a couple other people who had
some really wild ideas that at
first were somewhat accepted.
But as, uh, as he kept making observations
of all the finches on the Galapagos
Islands and all the turtles and all the
different creatures on there, it started
to make a little bit more sense, right?
So it took time, right?
It can be disproven.
Same thing, even with, uh, think of
the pandemic is a really good example
of how theories change real time
within the year 2020 through 2021.
The.
Idea of how COVID worked changed and
what we had to do to protect ourselves.
If you remember back in, uh,
early March, like they're thinking
like, Oh, just lock your doors to
stay, stay secluded for two weeks.
It'll be fine.
But then afterwards they're like,
Oh, it could be on surfaces.
All everybody was panicking.
So remember you might've been sanitizing
everything that came into your house.
You might've been wearing a full mask.
Some people were thinking
they needed gas masks.
They were going full on in.
And eventually they realize like,
Oh, you know, it is aerosol based.
You don't have to worry about surfaces.
And a cloth mask was enough, but then they
realized these particles are too small.
They go through cloth, right?
That doesn't quite, it's not effective.
So then they had the N95 masks.
They got, it's continued to improve.
It's falsifiable.
That's the whole idea.
And same thing even with
the vaccines, right?
The vaccine was, has gone
through many iterations.
And at first people were really
afraid it would be effective.
And that's because it's learned,
it's not, it's scientific
knowledge in progress, right?
It's moving really fast.
When it comes to this idea, coming to
chemistry back, back into the fold.
One thing that we were talking
about last video is that we're
going to be looking at particles.
Dalton's atomic theory of matter
is what I've been describing
earlier about how particles are
what make up all matter around us.
So all matter is made up of particles, and
these particles are referred to as atoms.
Now, atoms all have very
specific properties, right?
And they can be described via the
PRAC table and all your observations.
We're going to be learning about
that over the next few weeks
and how we can describe things.
But keep in mind, it's a theory.
It's something that could be disproven,
and that's the exciting part, right?
Learning something, we accepted it, we
all, all science accepted it as fact,
but it's something that, you know, if
it was disproven and we had the results
back up, the theory would evolve.
Right.
And that's one of the ideas.
Now, when it comes to these
theories, how do we describe them?
Well, observations require detail
and they're really important.
Now, one thing I'm going to see in
a lot of my videos is I'm not the
best artist, but I try my best.
I'm trying to make it so that it's
something that can be observed.
So how do we describe observation, right?
Qualitative And quantitative quantity
is the most important part of chemistry.
I like to say, and a lot of my colleagues
get mad at me is that chemistry is
kind of like an applied math class.
We're going to be doing a lot of
math, meaning you have to be able
to specific, specify the quantity.
So if I said I saw a whale as big as
my house, well, What does that mean?
Like, how big is the whale?
How, like, what size is your house?
It could be, it could be
a lot of things, right?
It could be a mansion.
It could be a normal sized home.
It could be an apartment, maybe.
It's like, I don't understand, right?
So when it comes to describing things Uh,
this is all about, we gotta use units.
So one thing that you're gonna be,
we're gonna be learning over the
next, uh, couple, several weeks and
throughout the whole semester is that
we need units to describe our thinking.
When it first comes to this, SI
units are very, very important.
We also have metric units as well, so that
we can describe the quantity of something.
And then it gives us a better
understanding of the quality that we saw.
So, when it comes to SI units, you have
meters, right, so the length of something.
You have kilograms, so
how heavy is something.
How can you actually look at a, if you go
to a mass balance and you measure the mass
of something, it's telling you exactly how
many atoms there are within that thing.
You can calculate that.
Kelvin is all about temperature.
Um, you're used to Fahrenheit in the U.
S.
Uh, in terms of the rest
of the world is Celsius.
So there are different scales, right?
So there's SI units.
And like I said, metric Celsius
is what's used when it comes
to normal math in the lab.
If we have to measure the time
of something, that's seconds.
And then if we have amount that's moles,
when it comes back to the metric units
will also be using leaders as volume.
So we'll be using all kinds of different.
Types of units to describe or think and
we need to start memorizing these you will
have a lot of reference sheets to help
You with us, but we need to be able to
start practicing with them and using them
very very often Now when it comes to these
units and as you start going through the
math of them and understanding How can
we present the numbers correctly, right?
one of the ideas of all science is that we
want to be able to speak the same language
and So that way, whether you're in the U.
S., or if you're in Europe, or
if you're in Asia, or in Russia,
or in China, or wherever, we're
all speaking the same system.
And that's one of the reasons
why the scientific community
uses the metric system in the U.
S., because the U.
S.
uses our own kinds of units.
We do our own thing, right?
We use miles, feet, um, pounds,
all these units that really are
not used by the rest of the world.
So we're trying to Make sure that we're
on the same page, so we'll have our units.
We'll also have prefixes as well
What prefixes do is they help define
the size so that way the number is?
More manageable to use so for example
if you have let's say one meter
right so which is approximately four
feet one meter is equivalent of 100
centimeters or 1000 millimeters Right.
So you can see how that scale
is changing, but they all rep,
they're all the same as one meter.
So that, that changes.
Kilogram is essentially saying that, okay,
if you have one kilogram, that's a, that
1000 grams a milliliter is 0.001 liters.
It's used to just to change the scale and
we're gonna be learning how to use those.
So be aware of that.
There are a lot of prefixes to define all
these to how, how does the scale work?
It will be used over time.
Um, so throughout the, uh, towards the
end of the, end of the, all the video
series, you will learn how to use these.
Now, the other thing is, like I mentioned,
we're in the US, but we're trying to
convert to metric because even, not only
our scientific communities, but la but
hospitals and clinics are now starting
to use metric even more so that way
it's applied to all countries, right?
We are a global community, we have to
speak a global language, so we will be
converting between different things.
This has been this video for now.
We are going to take these
observations and learn how to go
through the quantities of them.
And learn the math essentials behind
this, so that way you can learn those
math skills at Ace Chemistry, and
to be able to move forward and to do
really, really well in this class.
Thank you so much for watching, and I look
forward to seeing you in future videos.
Bye now.
See y'all later.